The best smartphone in the world and for
the world is finally coming to the USA,
but something just doesn't feel quite
right about it. This is the new
Fairphone 6. And normally here on
JerryRig Everything, we durability test
a smartphone before taking it apart. But
this particular smartphone is designed
to be taken apart. Designed to be
repaired and designed to be upgraded
with 8 years of security updates and a
5-year warranty. On paper, it sounds
like this modular Fairphone 6 is the
solution to all the world's problems.
But there's a catch for at least the
people who live in the USA. And we'll
get to that more in a minute. On the
back side, there is a subtle recess near
the lower edge. Kind of interesting. And
right above that, there are two
prominent T5 screws, which conceal the
user replaceable battery that's also
screwed in with five more of the same T5
screws. The battery of the Fairphone 6
can be replaced in about 2 minutes by
anyone with that Torx 5 screwdriver bit.
It's not quite as repairable as the
Fairphone 5 from 2 years ago, though,
which didn't need a screwdriver at all
to swap the battery. The Torque screws
kind of mess with the whole vibe that
the phone used to have. Now, there are
modular accessories for the back panel.
These all have braille on the box, and
since I'm a huge fan of accessibility,
thumbs up for that. The accessories
include a credit card module or finger
loop module or even some beefy screws
for a lanyard strap or your laboos. Now,
while I am disappointed that the
Fairphone 6 is less repairable than the
Fairphone 5, it's not the main reason
that I'm disappointed. The reason I'm
disappointed is because in Europe, this
phone costs an extremely reasonable
€599,
or about 700 bucks. The battery is 4,315
mAh, by the way, and there's a little
circular white water damage indicator at
the top of the battery slot. However,
getting back to the price of the phone,
the only way to officially get the
Fairphone 6 in the USA is to pay a third
party company called Marina $900,
$200 more than the rest of the world,
which doesn't have all that great of a
flavor. There are eight more silver T5
screws holding in the front display
panel, which is all you'll need to
remove and replace the screen, which
does bring back some of my happiness.
For reference, these replacement parts
are already available in Europe. The
battery is €40 and the screen is €9.
Very reasonable. And with even an
amateur level of screwing abilities, the
screen of the Fairphone 6 can be
replaced in about 5 minutes. But again,
no replacement parts are yet available
through Marina here in the USA, which
again makes me wonder why they released
the phone here in the first place since
spare parts are kind of the whole stick.
I am told the spare parts are coming
later in August of 2025, but based on
the pricing of the phone, they will
probably be far more expensive here in
the USA than over in Europe. The five
black T5 screws hold in the lower
plastics. This replacement piece cost
€25. and he comes up with the small
circular coin style vibrator motor as
well as the lower loudspeaker which does
not have any balls inside. There is
however an incredibly modular USBC 2.0
port that can charge at 30 watts.
There's a black rubber ring around the
port which helps with the IP55
waterresistant rating since protection
is always a good thing. There are six
more T5 screws up in the top plastics.
With those gone, we get our first look
at the motherboard and it's little
Easter egg which I'll get to in a
second. The top plastics come away with
their NFC coil. There is no wireless
charging. We also find that one of the
three camera rings on the back isn't
actually a camera. It's a 3D
timeofflight depth sensor, which is
fine. Apple uses these types of sensors
as well with their own cameras. The
Easter egg on the motherboard looks kind
of like an actual egg that's been broken
on the motherboard. But in reality, this
tattoo is actually a physical location,
only visible, of course, to the people
who tear down their phones or who are
subscribed here to my channel. It's a
map of the DRC, the Democratic Republic
of the Congo, and Fairphone is the
country immortalized on their
motherboard to highlight its commitment
to sourcing minerals responsibly. Since
the DRC is where we get a lot of our
cobalt, copper, and lithium, the main
camera is a 50 megapixel unit, which
does have optical image stabilization.
The camera right above that is a 13
megapixel ultrawide, which does not have
OIS, but that's normal among the
ultrawide cameras. And if we grab the
front-facing camera, unnapping it like a
little Lego, we can find the 32
megapixel does not have any OIS either.
There is however a modular stereo
earpiece speaker which has the
waterproofing mesh over the opening to
help protect the speaker internals. And
for 99% of everyone else on the planet,
this is where they would stop normal
repairs and in the tear down. However,
we aren't regular people, so we're going
to keep on going to see what kind of
cooling system the Fairphone 6 is
working with. Super cool that each of
the signal wires are colorcoded on the
motherboard. We've never seen that
before. And also, I almost forgot, we do
have the SIM card tray down here at the
bottom, which, and this is true, doubles
as an expandable storage tray.
You can expand the storage of the
Fairphone 6 up to 2 terb. The
motherboard does not have any screws of
its own, just pulls right up and out of
the frame. It's using recycled tin and
copper, and getting its other metals and
minerals from verified conflict-free
mining areas, like their name,
Fairphone, implies. It looks like the
thermal solution is just some soft
thermal foam on the back that pulls heat
from the motherboard and transfers it to
the aluminum mid-frame. There's also
some graphite on the screen side of the
frame and hopefully it can all survive
the full reassembly and durability test.
And yeah, of course, I get it. The world
doesn't revolve around the USA, but
having to pay an extra $200 kind of puts
the Fairphone 6 and its current specs
outside of a logical grasp for someone
in the USA. Anyway, one company that
does have the logical savings of your
wallet in mind though and actually gives
away his services for free for 90 days
is today's sponsor, Bit Defender. With
new AI scam text messages and AI videos
currently taking advantage of your
grandparents, online scamming has turned
into a very effective trillion dollar
industry. Scams delivered by text
message are the most popular these days.
And I even get those messages on my own
personal phone. One way to fight back is
with Bit Defender. They've been a global
leader in cyber security for the last
two decades, which means they're good at
catching these scams no matter what
country they emanate from. Bit Defender
has also added a new protective layer
for your digital life called Scam
Copilot. It's a new AI powered sidekick
that detects and fights sophisticated
online email and texting scams in real
time. And it's free for 90 days with the
link in the description. You can even
send the co-pilot screenshots of text
messages that you think might be scams.
And the scam co-pilot can let you or
your parents know what's safe. A smart
person such as yourself might understand
the difference between fishing and
fishing, but for sure your parents or
grandparents might not. With Bit
Defender, you can now protect your
family and your future inheritance on
five devices at the same time. You don't
have to take my word for it, though. Bit
Defender is already delivering
protection to millions of customers and
businesses worldwide. And it works on
iPhones, Androids, and of course, your
computers. It also gets you unlimited
VPN traffic, a password manager, and
identity protection. I'll leave a link
in the description for your free 90 days
of Bit Defender premium security
subscription. And thanks to Bit Defender
for sponsoring this video. One thing we
should talk about is the bright yellow
button on the side of the Fairphone 6.
It's actually a slider that instantly
turns your smartphone into a dumb phone.
And honestly, I think this is pretty
awesome. The first step to overcoming an
addiction is distancing yourself from
what you're addicted to. And I think
every phone should come with one of
these touch grasp buttons. With it all
fully assembled and every screw put back
into place, including the eight screws
around the edge of the screen and the
two visible screws on the back panel,
the phone should in theory be just as
strong now as the day it was born. Both
of which are today. All since it's
designed to be taken apart. Now, keep in
mind that everywhere else in the world,
this is a mid-range phone with a nearly
mid-range price point. But here in the
USA, it's a mid-range phone with a near
flagship price point, which completely
changes the vibe. You can see the
variable refresh rate on the 120 Hz
screen. It's not visible to the naked
eye, of course, but those 10 hertz
starts showing up at 60 fps, which is
what my main camera is filming with. The
Gorilla Glass 7i we see still scratches
at a level six with deeper grooves at a
level seven. The sides of the phone are
rather thick
and made from plastic, but thicker
phones do not bother me in the
slightest, so it's not a big deal. We
have our power button over here, as well
as the yellow plastic programmable
Fairphone Moment switch. Up at the top,
there is a small noiseancelling
microphone hole, but no antenna line
since the whole phone is plastic. The
earpiece slit is a tad wider than a
razor, but the grill itself won't ever
be falling out on its own.
The left side of the phone, besides just
being plastic, has volume buttons that
do come out from the frame. Now, I don't
think this will ever happen on accident,
but it is worth knowing, especially
since the buttons don't really want to
go back in their home once they come
out. Samsung's buttons click back in
pretty quick. I also noticed here that
everything on the screen has a weird
green tint to it, which is an
interesting theme for the phone to ship
with. Going into the menu and getting
rid of that hue, though, brought the
screen back to a normal color gradient.
Anyway,
the bottom of the phone has that SIM and
SD card tray along with a USBC 2.0 port,
which again, when you have the same
specs as an iPhone, you know you're at
least 3 years behind. Most Android
flagships are using USB 3.2, which
transfers data 10 times faster. But the
Fairphone is modular, so maybe they can
supply an upgraded port in the future.
Now, I'm not the biggest fan of torque
screws being the standard screw on a
so-called repairable smartphone. I do
agree that Torx are better. As you can
see from my orthographic projection,
they have six points, which give them
more gripping ability than a
four-pronged Phillips, and they're less
likely to strip or cam out, but they are
also less common, which means people
might not have these screwdriver bits
just laying around that they could use
for repairs. And I'm not quite sure the
less common bit size is worth the
trade-off. Both camera lenses and the
time of flight circle are protected with
glass, but the rest of everything else
on the back is made from plastic. The
screen, as we saw earlier, is a 6.3 in
LTPO with 1 billion colors, 1,400 nits,
and 120 Hz variable refresh rate, and
lasted about 35 seconds under the heat
for my lighter. And the OLED mostly
recovered. Finally, the bin test. Even
with the thick aluminum midframe and
screws up the wazoo, the Fairphone 6
does have some flex when bent from the
back and even more flex when bent from
the front. Those two rear screws are
holding on for dear life. No two screws
have ever done more work in the history
of smartphones. But thanks to those two
specifically putting in overtime, the
Fairphone 6 lives to see another day. I
don't know if it's the US tariffs, the
middlemen involved, or if Fairphone just
doesn't like shipping internationally,
but it's a bummer we can't have those
lower prices on this side of the pond.
But congrats to the rest of the world,
though. You got a winner with this one.
Thanks a ton for watching. I'll see you